A Guide to World War I Papers and Memorabilia Chiefly Regarding Thomas R. Pleucker 1914-1930
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
World War I Papers and Memorabilia Chiefly Regarding Thomas R. Pleucker 1914-1930
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10875-r
188 items
The collection consists of ca. 188 papers and memorabilia chiefly pertaining to Thomas Pleucker, including a bust portrait, glass lantern slides, children's alphabet blocks, drawings, newspapers, certificates, posters, and letters.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items were given to the University of Virginia Library Joseph M. Bruccoli Great War Collection by Mrs. Michael Lazare, New Milford, Connecticut, through Matthew J. Bruccoli, Columbia, South Carolina, on September 27, 1993.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the Joseph M. Bruccoli Great War Collection consists of ca. 188 items, ca. 1914-1930, including a bust portrait of Francis Ledwidge, "Lance Corporal Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers," with a quote from a Ledwidge letter to Lord Dunsany; about 109 glass lantern slides of the Great War and other scenes; "ABC Picture Blocks," a set of children's alphabet blocks, each bearing on one side a paper slip with the letter of the alphabet, and on the other side, a slip bearing a halftone reproduction of a colored drawing of a World War I personality or item still in its original sales box and protected in a new storage box; a single copy of The Mehun News, May 16, 1919, a weekly newspaper published by Ordnance Troops at Atelier de Mehun-sur-Yevre, France, with poetry, travel articles, photographs, cartoons, and histories of ordnance units (transferred to Rare Books); and a photograph "showing how French 270 mm. guns are brought up to new positions as Allied drive advances" by Underwood and Underwood, New York.
Also present are ten military promotion and memorial certificates and posters, 1916-1919, pertaining to two American soldiers, of Oneida County, New York, George A. Laurin and Lloyd J. Laurin, who was killed in action on July 21, 1918, at Soissons, France, as a private, Supply Company, 2nd Ammunition Train. These include rosters for Troop "D" 6th Cavalry, Fort Sam Houston, San Antonio, Texas, listing George A. Laurin as a sergeant, and a roster for Troop "I" Fifth Cavalry, Camp Stewart, Fort Bliss, Texas, listing Lloyd J. Laurin as a private.
There are about seventy letters and other items regarding an American soldier, Thomas R. Pluecker (1892-1918) of Nacogdoches, Texas, who died of pneumonia at the American Expeditionary Force Base Hospital No. 17 shortly after arriving in France, on September 13, 1918, as a member of the Machine Gun Company, 64th U.S. Infantry. All of the letters are on patriotic or Knights of Columbus stationery, and are from Pluecker to his family, including his brother, Angus R. Pluecker, sister, Madie Pluecker, and his mother, Mrs. J.T. Pluecker, expressing concern for the family and the farm, mentioning his attendance at Roman Catholic religious services, and praising the activities of the Knights of Columbus and the Red Cross on behalf of the soldiers. He began his training at Camp Travis, San Antonio, as part of the [45th ?] Company, 12th Brigade, but was transferred to Camp MacArthur, Waco, Texas, 7th Division, Machine Gun Company, 64th Infantry, by July 20, 1918. By July 26, 1918, Pluecker was at Camp Merritt, New Jersey, after a five day train ride, and in a letter dated August 20, 1918, he mentions that he had previously left for France but was returned to Camp Mills, Long Island, New York, after a sub attack on the fourth day of the voyage. On August 28, 1918, his company left for France for the second time.
Index of Glass Lantern Slides
Aisne (L-1391, 1474)
Alsace (L-1395, 1454, 1478)
Arras (L-1389, 1452, 1463, 1475)
Artois (L-1390, 1431, 1451, 1468, 1472)
Benevoie (L-1385, 1407)
Bitschwiller (L-1428, 1450)
Cartoons (L-1378-1382, 1417, 1483)
Chalons (L-1466)
Clermont-in-Argonne (L- 1448)
Gerardmer (L-1465)
London (L-1430, 1439)
Oise (L-1400, 1449)
Paris (L-1381, 1382, 1415, 1477)
Remiremont (L-1394)
Rheims (L-1464, L- 1473)
Rome: the Catacombs (L-1387, 1388, 1406, 1445-1447)
Scheldt River (L-1426)
Soissons (L-1399)
Suez Canal (L-1412, 1429)
Verdun (L-1416, 1442)
Contents List
- Correspondence of Thomas R. Pluecker 1918 Jul-Sep, 3 folders
- Miscellaneous Correspondence & Material concerning Thomas R. Pluecker & his death 1916-1930
- Francis Ledwidge, "Lance corpl. Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers," Bust Portrait, Matted with quote from a Ledwidge letter to Lord Dunsany n.d.
- Photograph showing how French 270 mm guns are brought up to new positions as Allied drive advances by Underwood & Underwood, New York 1916 Jul 10
- "ABC Picture Blocks" with scenes from the Great War ca. 1914-1919
- Ten military certificates, posters, and rosters pertaining to Lloyd J. Laurin and George A. Laurin ca. 1916-1919
- Glass Lantern Slides, L-1375 to L-1484
  - Sinking of the Bluecher, L-1375
  - Shell Fire, L-1376 & 1377
  - Cartoon "We Are Expecting to Leave This Place at Any Moment", L-1378 & L-1379
  - Cartoon "Full Marching Order What Your Kit Feels Like After Ten Miles!", L-1380
  - Cartoon "Fright in Paris" La Colonne Vendome/La Tour Eiffel Se Gondole, L-1381 & L-1382
  - French Soldiers on Out-Post, L-1383
  - German Shell - Exploded, L-1384
  - Benevoie: Japanese Red Cross Hospital, L-1385
  - Waiting for the Taube, L-1386
  - Roma: Cemeterio dei Cappuccini, L-1387 & L-1388
  - Arras: Ruins, L-1389
  - Artois: Gas Bomb, L-1390
  - Aisne: Barbed Wire Protecting a French Trench, L-1391
  - French General Sarrait receives an English Delegation, L-1392
  - Rest for French Infantry Regiment, L-1393
  - Remiremont: German Prisoners, L-1394
  - Alsace: British Ambulance, L-1395
  - Soldier in Dugout, L-1396
  - Soldiers in dugout, L-1397
  - Haystack & Sniper, L-1398
  - Soissons: Mayor Mme. Macherez during German Occupation, L-1399
  - Oise: Entrance to Mine Shaft, L-1400
  - X-ray of Shattered Wrist, L-1401
  - Barn Interior, L-1402
  - Bringing Up Shells from Dugout, L-1403
  - "End of Poor Dobbin", L-1404
  - Life Belt Notice on R.M.S. Lapland, L-1405
  - Roma: Cemeterio dei Cappuccini, L-1406
  - Benvoie: Japanese Red Cross Hospital, L-1407
  - French Cannon, Army Museun, Campaign 1914-1915, L-1408
  - Airplance, B.E. Type, Two Seater, Fitted w/ Wireless, L-1409
  - Ancient Bow & Arrow Gun, L-1410
  - Modern Surgery, Example of, L-1411
  - Suez Canal: British Cruiser firing a broadside at the Turks, L-1412
  - The King of the Belgians Among His Soldiers, L-1413
  - French Observation Balloon, L-1414
  - Paris: Enemy Airplane on Exhibit, Hotel des Invalides, L-1415
  - Verdun: Unexploded German Shell (420 mm.), L-1416
  - Cartoon "Full Marching Order - What Your Kit Feels Like After Ten Miles!", L-1417
  - "Comedy at the Front", L-1418
  - Hospital Scene - Dentists with Patients, L-1419
  - Hosptical Scene - Patients at Recreation, L-1420
  - Hospital Scene - Doctor in Laboratory, L-1421
  - Hospital Scene - Nurses with Patients, L-1422
  - Hospital Scene - Patients Enjoying Fresh Air, L-1423
  - Hospital Scene - Examination of Patients, L-1424
  - Hospital Scene - Nurses in Patient Ward, L-1425
  - Scheldt River, Germany: Pontoon Bridge, L-1426
  - French Anti-aircraft Battery, L-1427
  - Bitschwiller: Factory Ruined by Retreating Germans, L-1428
  - Suez Canal: British Cruiser Firing Upon Turks, L-1429
  - London: War Office, L-1430
  - Artois, France: Moroccan Band, L-1431
  - French Soldiers Doing Hand Laundry, L-1432 & L-1433
  - Shell Pit - Shell Being Set for Firing, L-1434
  - One of the Latest Destroyers Viewed from Biplane, L-1435
  - Life Rafts, L-1436
  - On Shipboard, L-1437
  - "On the Davits", L-1438
  - London: Admiralty Arch, L-1439
  - On Shipboard near the davits, L-1440
  - Chapel at the Front Used as Temporary Hospital, L-1441
  - Verdun: Unexploded German Shell, L-1442
  - French Ovens, L-1443 & L-1444
  - Rome: Catacombs, L-1445-1447
  - Clermont-in-Argonne: Ruins, L-1448
  - Oise: Resting in a Dugout, L-1449
  - Bitschwiller: Factory Ruins, L-1450
  - Artois: 220 mm. Mortar, L-1451
  - Arras: Burned Out Vehicle, L-1452
  - French General Frenchet of Esperey, L-1453
  - Alsace: Troop Food Supplies Carried by Cattle, L-1454
  - French Hospital, L-1455
  - Lounge & Bath at the Front, L-1456
  - French Hospital, L-1457 & L-1458
  - Medal Pinning Ceremony, L-1459
  - "Comedy at the Front", L-1460
  - Binocular in Pieces, L-1461
  - Arras: City Hall, L-1463
  - Rheims School, near Rheims Cathedral, L-1464
  - Gerardmer: German Prisoners, L-1465
  - Chalons, France: Algerian Cavalrymen, L-1466
  - Shell Burst, L-1467
  - Artois: Cannon Taken from the Germans, L-1468
  - French Field Telephone, L-1469
  - Hydroplane leaving H.M.S. Hibernia, L-1470
  - Chemical Factory Set on Fire by the Belgians, L-1471
  - Artois: Captured German Machine Guns, L-1472
  - Rheims: Natives Take Refuge in Cellar, L-1473
  - Aisne: Village Entrance, L-1474
  - Arras: Cathedral, L-1475
  - Algerian Music Corps, L-1476
  - Paris: Picture of Dirigible Over the Arche de Triumphe, Paris, L-1477
  - Alsace: Removal of Mortar (glass cracked), L-1478
  - Ancient Box and Arrow Gun (glass cracked), L-1479
  - French 75 mm. Cannon (glass cracked), L-1480
  - Dentist with Patients (glass cracked), L-1481
  - Ships (glass cracked), L-1482
  - American Political Cartoon concerning Secretary Daniels & Congress Building a Navy (glass cracked), L-1483
  - Barn (glass cracked), L-1484